Finding Aid for Homer Ferguson Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- Senate Career, 1942-1954; 13.5 linear feet
  - Committees
    - Pearl Harbor (Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack)
      - Topical Files
        - McCollum, A.H. (Box 10)
          (mostly handwritten notes and questions)
        - Marshall, George, 2 folders (Box 10)
          (mostly questions, testimony, and documents)
        - Miles, Sherman (Box 10)
          (mostly lists of questions; documents; and testimony)
        - Minority Report (incomplete) (Box 10)
        - Naiden, Mary (Box 10)
        - Naval Duties, Division of (Box 10)
        - "Notes On Majority Report,", July 19, 1946 (Box 10)
        - Noyes, L. (Box 10)
          (mostly typewritten notes)
        - Orders of Proof, Committee (Box 10)
        - Phillips, Colonel (Box 10)
          (statement and lists of questions)
        - Resolutions Committee, 4 folders (Box 10)
        - Richardson, James O. (Box 10)
          (mostly lists of questions)
        - Roberts, Owen J. (Box 10)
          (material re: Roberts Commission)
        - Rochefort, Joseph J. (Box 10)
          (affidavit, and handwritten notes)
        - Roosevelt, Franklin D.: Committee Access to his Papers and Files (Box 10)
        - Sadtler, Otis K. (Box 10)
        - Safford, L.F. (Box 10)
          (statement; lists of questions; documents)
        - Schuirman, R.E. (Box 10)
          (testimony, and lists of questions)
        - Short, Walter C. (Box 10)
          (mostly lists of questions, and materials re: his retirement)
        - Smith, Bedell (Box 10)
        - Smith, George H.E.: Secretary, Republican Steering Committee (Box 10)
          (several interesting letters to Ferguson)
        - Standley, Admiral (Box 10)
        - Stark, Harold (Box 11)
          (mostly testimony; lists of questions; and documents)
        - State Department Documents (miscellaneous), 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Stimpson, Henry (Box 11)
          (mostly statements, and lists of questions)
        - Toulmin, Harry (Box 11)
          (one letter to Ferguson)
        - Turner, Richard (Box 11)
          (testimony; handwritten notes; and questions)
        - Wainwright, Jonathan (Box 11)
        - War Plans (Box 11)
        - Warning Messages:, November 26-27, 1941 (Box 11)
          (handwritten notes)
        - Welles, Sumner (Box 11)
          (handwritten notes, and includes draft of interesting Ferguson letter to New York Times)
        - Wilkinson, T.S. (Box 11)
          (mostly handwritten notes, and questions)
        - Winds Message (Box 11)
        - Witnesses (Box 11)
          ("Revised Order Of Proof And List Of Witnesses, And Explanatory Memoranda": by retiring Committee counsel for new counsel)
        - Wyman, Theodore (Box 11)
        - Zacharias, Ellis (Box 11)
        - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence
    Under the heading Correspondence, the researcher will find incoming and outgoing letters arranged chronologically by year. The former cover a variety of routine matters, while the latter deal mostly with travel related concerns: preparation; hospitality; and contacting the families of servicemen he met while abroad. Martin Gold, Hong Kong businessman, wrote frequently to Ferguson about the political and economic situation in the Far East.
    - Undated, 1947-1949 (Box 11)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 11)
      (Martin Gold)
    - 1950 (Box 11)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 11)
    - December 1951-January 1952 (Box 11)
      (samples of letters to families of servicemen visited on 1951-1952 trip to Korea)
  - Legislative Record
    Ferguson's Legislative Record (amendments offered; bills and joint resolutions introduced; motions and resolutions offered; reports; and remarks) and Voting Record (key votes; agriculture; appropriations; defense production act; education and welfare; foreign policy; labor; military and veterans; miscellaneous and administrative; and taxes and economic policy) are crucial to understanding where he stood on the major issues of his day.
    - Record Books, 2 volumes (Box 12)
  - Public Addresses
    Also important to an understanding of Ferguson's career in the Senate are his public addresses, which took the form of speeches, statements, releases, and radio broadcasts.
    - Undated (Box 12)
    - 1943-1946 (Box 12)
    - 1947 (Box 12)
    - 1948 (Box 12)
    - 1949 (Box 12)
    - 1950 (Box 12)
    - 1951, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1952, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1953, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1954, 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Topical Files
    In the Topical Files subseries, the researcher will find the biographical materials relating to Ferguson's senate career of interest, as well as those items that shed light on the often stormy relationship between Drew Pearson and the Senator (see Coplan, Pearson, and Thomas files). The correspondence and documents found in the Herbert Hoover file reveal a close relationship between the two men, in which Ferguson often times served as a conduit for making public the views of the former president on various topics. And the researcher should also note Ferguson's accounts of his various trips (see Diaries, and Travel).
    - Biographical, 2 folders (Box 13)
      (materials re: Ferguson's career as a Senator, often used in his reelection campaigns)
    - Brannan Program (Box 13)
      (lengthy statement expressing opposition to the program--author unknown)
    - Bricker Amendment (Box 13)
      (sample letter re: Ferguson's views on the amendment)
    - Brown, Prentiss M. (re: Truman appointment) (Box 13)
    - Clark, Tom (Box 13)
      (mostly documents re: his appointment to the Supreme Court, 1949)
    - Commonwealth Parliamentary Association Conference: Australia (report on), 1950 (Box 14)
    - Communism (Box 14)
      (miscellaneous materials, includes some correspondence, mostly related to communists in government)
    - Coplon, Judith (Box 14)
      (correspondence; clippings; statement re: Drew Pearson/Tom Clark/Ferguson controversy over Coplon)
    - Copper (Box 14)
      (mostly correspondence re: closing down of Michigan copper mines, 1945)
    - Cullum, Dyke (Box 14)
      (re: commodity speculation)
    - Defense Spending (Box 14)
      (1954 letter from C.E. Wilson, and draft of "A Nation Secure-Today and Tomorrow" speech)
    - Democratic Party of Michigan (Box 14)
      (press release (?) re: controversy over Post Office jobs/financial contributions)
    - Department of Defense (Box 14)
      (undated list of questions from Ferguson)
    - Diaries (Box 14)
      (mostly recorded during Senatorial trips)
    - Education and Exchange Programs (Box 14)
    - Elections
      - 1942 (Box 14)
        (letter from Prentiss Brown re: setting up debates)
      - 1948, 2 folders (Box 14)
        (includes materials re: Democratic request for recount)
      - 1954 (Box 14)
    - Expatriation Act, 1954 (Box 14)
      (mostly drafts of the bill)
    - Foreign Aid, 1947 (Box 14)
      (Ferguson letter to Styles Bridges re: Herter Select Committee on Foreign Aid report, and copy of report)
    - Foreign Countries: Collected Documents
      - Arabia-Egypt (Box 14)
      - India-Spain (Box 14)
    - Formosa, 1949 (Box 14)
      (Ferguson letter to Truman re: defense of Formosa, and Truman's routine response)
    - Hoover, Herbert (Box 14)
      (contains interesting correspondence between Hoover and Ferguson)
    - Information Program In The Far East (Box 14)
      (one letter, and report on trip to investigate the program)
    - Internal Security Law (Box 14)
    - Keyserling, Leon (Box 14)
      (letter to Ferguson re: alleged Communist sympathies of Keyserling's wife)
    - McCarthy, Joseph (Box 14)
      (interesting letter from Karl Mundt to Senators Ferguson and Knowland re: Army-McCarthy hearings)
    - McKeehan, Carl (Box 14)
      (William Rogers letter re: consideration of McKeehan for position as U.S. Marshal)
    - Masonry (statement on: "As I See Masonry Today") (Box 14)
    - Motor Carrier Claims Commission, 1949 (Box 14)
    - Pearson, Drew (Box 14)
      (mostly clippings, but also contains interesting correspondence re: Pearson/Ferguson antagonisms
    - Porter, Paul (Box 14)
      (mostly material re: investigation of his background and connection with The League For Industrial Democracy)
    - Rationing (questions, and interview) (Box 14)
    - Recess Appointments (Box 14)
    - Republican Conference (Box 14)
      (letter from Milton Young, Secretary explaining his reasons for resigning)
    - Thomas, Elmer (Box 14)
      (material re: probe of his stock/commodity transactions: includes interesting letter from Drew Pearson)
    - Travel (Box 14)
    - Trip Around The World, 1950; 2 folders (Box 14)
      (includes clippings, press conference transcripts, journey account, and report by Ferguson)
    - Vincent, John Carter (Box 14)
      (citizen mail re: his loyalty investigation, and Ferguson replies)
    - White, Harry Dexter (Box 14)
      (citizen mail and Ferguson replies)
    - World Food Situation (Box 14)
  - Voting Record, 1943-1953
    - File arranged primarily by topic (Box 14)
- Interregnum:, November 1954-April, 1955; 13 folders
  The Interregnum: November 1954 - April 1955 (13 folders) series is comprised of correspondence that falls in that period after Ferguson's defeat for re-election and before his taking over the Philippines Ambassadorship. It is arranged chronologically by month and year, and covers a variety of rather routine matters. The researcher should note, however, that in the November 1954 files there is interesting constituent mail regarding both the Senator's defeat and the censure of Joseph McCarthy, and enlightening replies from Ferguson (although brief and form letter in nature).
  - 1954
    - November 1954, 9 folders (Box 15)
      (Contains interesting constituent mail re: election, and censure of Joseph McCarthy; also interesting, although brief and form letter in nature, Ferguson replies)
    - December 1954 (Box 15)
  - 1955
    - January 1955 (Box 15)
    - February 1955 (Box 15)
    - March-April 1955 (Box 15)
- Hoover Commission, 1953-1955
  The Hoover Commission series files (1953-1955; 0.5 linear ft.) are arranged chronologically and are comprised of the following types of materials, all of which are directly related to the work of the Commission: clippings; correspondence; staff and organizational information; minutes; press releases; task force reports; and memoranda to Ferguson from Lawrence Lindemer, Ferguson's committee assistant.
  - Undated (Box 15)
  - 1953, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - 1954, 3 folders (Box 15)
  - 1955 (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
    (materials acquired/issued by Ferguson while on the Court of Military Appeals)
- Philippines Ambassadorship, 1955-1956; 1 linear foot
  The Philippines Ambassadorship series (1955-1956; 1 linear ft.) contains materials that provide only a general picture of Ferguson's tenure as ambassador. Most of the correspondence, organized alphabetically by last name, concerns visits to the islands by various individuals, social functions to which the Fergusons were invited, or events of a personal nature that were of interest to the Ambassador and his wife. As with much of Ferguson's correspondence, any thoughts on his role or duties as ambassador are stated only in the broadest of terms. The researcher might be interested in the Diary, which is actually a daily listing of the Ambassador's appointments, and in the three scrapbooks, which contain clippings about the Fergusons taken from Philippine newspapers.
  - Appointment (samples of congratulatory letters and Ferguson replies) (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 8 folders (Box 16)
  - Credentials (Box 16)
  - Diary ("Ambassador's Diary": daily appointments schedule), April 7, 1955-March 16, 1956; 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Douglas, William O. Visit (clippings) (Box 16)
  - Speeches (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Scrapbooks, 3 volumes (Box 16)
- United States Court Of Military Appeals, 1956-1976; 5 linear feet
  The United States Court of Military Appeals (1956-1976; 5 linear ft.) series is comprised of Correspondence, Discs, Public Addresses, and Topical Files.
  - Correspondence
    Letters to and from friends; servicemen requesting aid (the majority of which are referred elsewhere); and invitations and thank you notes comprise the bulk of the Correspondence files, which are arranged alphabetically by last name.
    - A-L, 15 folders (Box 17)
    - M-Z, 11 folders (Box 18)
      (P folder contains correspondence re pledge of allegiance; W folder under Wedemeyer had interesting correspondence regarding Watergate; W folder under John T. Willis included transcript of interview on courts which HF would not approve for publication because it was too incomplete)
  - Public Addresses (speeches, television, testimony)
    The Public Addresses are arranged chronologically by year and pertain to a variety of judicial and legislative concerns.
    - Discs: Edison Voicewriter (Box 25)
      Both the Correspondence and Topical files can be supplemented by the Edison Voicewriter Discs, on which Ferguson dictated letters, memos, and conference notes. Some of the discs are undated; the majority of the ones that are dated are from the late 1950s.
    - Speeches
      - Undated, 1956-1971; 12 folders (Box 25)
        (lacks speeches for 1965)
        (audiotape of 1967 speech located under Sound Recordings in box 25)
    - Television Appearance, 1961 (Box 18)
      (materials re: Junior Bar Association TV Program)
    - Testimony, Congressional
      - Appropriations Committee, 1962-1972 (Box 19)
      - Judiciary Committee: Subcommittee on Constitutional Rights of Military Personnel, 1963 (Box 19)
      - Post Office and Civil Service Committee, 1961 (Box 19)
        (re: job upgrade for R. Tedrow)
  - Topical Files
    Of most interest to the researcher should be the Topical files, and in particular the files on cases from the October Term, 1970-1971. It is the only term which is well documented in the collection, and in the files can be found conference notes (although difficult to read), case summaries, opinion drafts, and memoranda from Ferguson's law clerk regarding recommended action. Of additional interest in the Topical files are the Memoranda files, which shed light on the internal workings of the Court, and the files on the Uniform Code of Military Justice, from which the researcher can determine Court views on proposed Code changes.
    - Ad Hoc Committee for Military Justice, Department of the Army, 1960-1961 (Box 19)
    - American Bar Association: Section on Judicial Administration, Committee on Federal Legislation (Box 19)
      (materials re: Ferguson's work on the committee and his support for the minority report)
    - Annual Reports (Box 19)
      (not a complete run)
    - Appointment to Court (Box 19)
      (includes John Foster Dulles letter offering the appointment to Ferguson)
    - Articles about the Court (Box 19)
      (includes one written by Ferguson)
    - Cases
      - Individuals
        - Anderson, Clayton, 1968 (Box 19)
          (re: question of whether U.S. was at war on November 3, 1964)
        - Davies, Edward R (Box 19)
        - Gallagher vs. Quinn, et al., 1966 (Box 19)
          (mostly appeals, motions, and replies)
        - O'Callahan vs. Parker, 1969 (Box 19)
          (materials re: U.S. Supreme Court decision and consequences for Military Court of Appeals)
        - Wright, J.C., 1967 (Box 19)
          (re: admissibility of voice print machine evidence)
      - October Term, 1970-1971; 5 folders (Box 19)
        (includes conference notes; summaries; handwritten notes; memoranda from Ferguson's law clerk re: recommended action; and some opinion drafts)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
    - Histories of the Court (covering 1951-1961) (Box 20)
    - Judge Advocate General's School, U.S. Army (Box 20)
    - Memoranda
      (mostly to Ferguson/members of the court from court clerks and commissioners)
      - Undated (Box 20)
      - 1953-1956 (Box 20)
      - 1957 (Box 20)
      - 1958-1961 (Box 20)
      - 1962-1966, 1968-1969; 1971; 1972 (Box 20)
    - Mohbat, Joseph, 1962; 2 folders (Box 20)
      (A.P. article on Ferguson and citizen mail, mostly concerning relatives in need of assistance)
    - Opinions
      - Dissenting to Denials of Petition for Review, 1970-1971; 3 folders (Box 20)
        (includes rough drafts of most opinions, primarily from 1970-1971, but also from the 1960s)
      - Format of (Box 20)
      - Synopses of, 1961/62-1968/69 (Box 20)
    - Personnel Matters (Box 20)
    - Proulx, Alfred: Clerk of the Court (Box 20)
      (mostly Proulx responses to correspondence from servicemen to Ferguson)
    - Retirement (Box 20)
    - Rules of Practice and Procedure (Box 20)
      (drafts, memoranda, final versions)
    - Statistics (miscellaneous) (Box 20)
    - Taft, Robert, Oral History Project (Box 20)
    - Travel (Box 20)
    - Uniform Code of Military Justice
      - Army Ad Hoc Committee on Military Justice, 1960-1961; 2 folders (Box 20)
        (materials re: the report and the Court response)
      - Congressional Investigations, 1962-1967 (Box 21)
      - Proposed Changes
        - 1956 (Box 21)
        - 1957 (Box 21)
        - 1958 (Box 21)
          (contains interesting material re: Ferguson's views on Court changes)
        - 1959 (Box 21)
        - 1961 (Box 21)
        - 1962 (Box 21)
        - 1963-1964 (Box 21)
        - 1972 (Box 21)
        - 1974 (Box 21)
        - 1975 (Box 21)
    - Vietnam Trip, 1967 (Box 21)
      (unknown if trip was taken, include itinerary and explanatory letter)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
- Inter-Parliamentary Union, 1949-1972; 0.3 linear feet
  The Inter-Parliamentary Union (1949-1972; 0.3 linear ft.) series is limited in both scope and content. Correspondence of a general nature, clippings, and documents related to Union conferences can be found here.
  - Various materials, 1949-1972 (Box 21)
- Clippings, 1 linear foot
  Clippings (scattered dates; 1 linear ft.) covers Ferguson's career. The series is currently unprocessed.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 22)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (3 linear ft.; ca. 1940s-ca. 1970s) of the collection nicely compliments the manuscript series. It is arranged under ten headings: Personal; Senate Career; Interregnum 1954-1955; Philippines Ambassadorship; United States Court of Military Appeals; Inter-Parliamentary Union; Date Unknown; Negatives; Film; and Albums. Under each heading, the pictures are arranged alphabetically by topic. The researcher is advised to check both the Date Unknown files and the Albums when having difficulty finding a particular picture elsewhere in the series. Negatives from the collection have been grouped together, and notations on the finding aid indicate when the researcher should examine them for matches with existing positives, or for additional images related to a particular phase of Ferguson's career.
  - Personal
    - Homer Ferguson Portraits
      - Formal, 2 folders (Box 23)
        (also see over oversize folder Ac)
      - Informal, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Myrtle Ferguson
      - General, 3 folders (Box 23)
        (includes photograph with Pat Nixon)
        (see also Philippines)
      - Portraits (Box 23)
        (see also Negatives)
    - Fergusons: Homer and Myrtle: Portraits, Formal and Informal (Box 23)
    - Hunting (Box 23)
  - Senate Career
    - Activities, General (Box 23)
    - Ann Arbor Aircraft Parts Production Corporation (Box 23)
    - Appearances (Box 23)
    - Bill Signings (with President Eisenhower) (Box 23)
    - Bond-a-Month Drive, 1953 (Box 23)
    - Brucker, Wilbur (with Ferguson) (Box 23)
    - Campaigns
      - General (Box 23)
      - 1954 (Box 23)
    - Colleagues and Friends, 4 folders (Box 23)
      (includes fellow Senators and Representatives such as Gerald Ford, Richard Nixon, Hubert Humphrey, Charles Potter, Lyndon Johnson, etc.)
    - Committees
      - Appropriations
        - General (Box 23)
        - Subcommittees
          - Federal Loyalty Program; Grain Speculation and Commodity Trading (Box 23)
          - World Wide Fact Finding Trip, 1949
            - London; Paris; Rome (Vatican); Germany (Bremerhaven) (Box 23)
            - Ankara, Turkey; Cairo, Egypt; Baghdad, Iraq (Box 23)
            - Peshawar, Pakistan; New Delhi, India (Box 23)
            - Rangoon, Burma; Batavia, Indonesia; Manila, Philippines (Box 23)
            - Korea; Thailand (Box 23)
            - Japan (Box 23)
      - Foreign Relations (Box 23)
      - Judiciary (Box 23)
      - National Defense (Special Committee Investigating The National Defense Program)
        (see also Albums)
        - Aircraft Assembly Plants (Box 23)
        - Caribbean Maneuvers, 1949 (Box 23)
        - Chrysler Corporation: War Contract Album (Box 23)
        - Consolidated Vultee Corporation (Box 23)
        - Hughes-Kaiser Hearings (Box 23)
        - Inter-American Highway, 2 folders (Box 23)
        - Meyers Investigation (Box 23)
        - Naval Base Inspections (Box 23)
        - Panama Canal Department (Box 23)
        - Reunion, 1959 (Box 23)
        - Taiwan: Chinese Army Training Photos (Box 23)
        - Willow Run Housing (Box 23)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
      - Pearl Harbor (Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack) (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - Constituents, 4 folders (Box 23)
    - Dayan, Moshe: Visit, 1954 (Box 23)
    - Detroit Birthday Festival, 1951 (Box 23)
      (includes Ferguson with Blair Moody, Harry Truman, and G. Mennen Williams)
    - Dulles, John Foster (with Ferguson) (Box 23)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight David, 2 folders (Box 23)
      (see also oversize folder Ac)
    - Groups-Unidentified (Box 23)
    - Green, Dwight (Box 23)
      (see Lincoln, Abraham)
    - Higgins, Harry (President, Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company) (Box 23)
    - Hoover, J. Edgar (Box 23)
      (see oversize folder Ac)
    - Lincoln, Abraham: Visit to Lincoln's Home, 1945 (Box 23)
    - Media Appearances: Radio and Television (Box 23)
    - Military Bases and Personnel
      - General, 2 folders (Box 23)
        (includes photograph with Joseph McCarthy)
      - U.S. Army: FP-136 Launching., August 7, 1943 (Box 23)
    - Plant Tours (Box 23)
    - Republican Party, 2 folders (Box 23)
      (includes photographs with Robert Taft, and Arthur Vandenberg)
    - Saint Lawrence Seaway
      - General (Box 23)
        (includes photograph with Harry Kelly)
      - Bill Signing (with President Eisenhower) (Box 23)
    - Social Events (Box 23)
    - Travel
      - Japan: Camp Chitose, 1950 (Box 23)
      - Korea: Official Visits, 1949-1952; 4 folders (Box 23)
      - Pakistan (picture of H.H. The Khan of Kalat) (Box 23)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
    - Vandenberg, Arthur (Box 23)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 23)
  - Interregnum
    - Various, 1954-1955 (Box 23)
      (includes picture of Hoover Commission)
  - Philippines Ambassadorship
    - Aguinaldo, Maria and Emilio (Box 24)
    - Ambuklao Hydroelectric Project, Baguio (Box 24)
    - American Embassy (Box 24)
    - American School: 35th Anniversary (Box 24)
    - Anonas Barrio (Box 24)
    - Bacolad City: Joint Induction of Philippine Jr. Chamber of Commerce and Bacolad Junior Chamber of Commerce; Negros Occidental, July 2, 1955 (Box 24)
    - Bulacan and Nueva Ecija (Box 24)
    - Brucker, Wilbur M (Box 24)
    - Caltex (Box 24)
    - Cebu City (Box 24)
    - Central Luzon Agricultural College
      - General (Box 24)
      - Souvenir of Citizenship Day: Photo Album (Box 24)
    - Dirksen, Everett: Visit (Box 24)
    - Douglas, William O.: Visit (Box 24)
    - Dumaguette (Box 24)
    - Entertainment, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Ferguson, Myrtle: General, 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Ferguson, Homer and Myrtle (Box 24)